Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*. Today's דף daf, *daf* is ק"ל *Kuf
Lamed* and the new פרק perek *perek* רבי אליעזר דמילה Rabbi Eliezer
d'Mila, *Rabi Eliezer De-Milah*, but we still have some wrapping up to
do from yesterday. So we pick up on קכ"ט עמוד ב' *Kuf
Kaf Tet amud bet*. The
so again, we start קכ"ט עמוד ב' *Kuf Kaf Tet amud bet*
and we are where are we about אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel,
*Amar Shmuel*. One, two, three, four, five, six lines down, end of
the line. אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel, *Amar Shmuel*. So we're talking about
different issues related to health because the end of the פרק perek
*perek* dealt with a woman giving childbirth and how she's in a
status of סכנת נפשות sakannas nefashos. *sakanas nefashos* and you can violate
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* for her well-being. So relating to similar issues, we
were talking about bloodletting, which is a standard practice that they did
for health-related issues, but also ones that they recognized that after the
fact made the person vulnerable. So let's take a look. אמר שמואל
*Amar Shmuel* said שמואל *Shmuel*, excuse me, פורסא דדמא כל
תלתין יומין *Porsa de-dama kol tlasin yomin*. The
the like this period of blood is thirty days, which basically means
that you don't let blood twice in one month. When when does
the Red Cross let you give again? Like every sixty ninety days.
Okay. This says thirty days between bloodletting. וביני פרקים ימעיט *U-veina perakim
yema'et*. Between the chapters, you should even do less. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says it means after you turn forty, assuming like a lifespan of
eighty years. וביני פרקים *U-veina perakim* and then between the remaining chapters,
meaning after you turn sixty, this is the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
reads it, יחזוב וימעיט *yachzov ve-yema'et*. You should do even give less.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says go to one every two months or once
every three months. ואמר שמואל *Ve-amar Shmuel*: פורסא דדמא חד בשבתא, ארבע
ומעלי שבתא *Porsa de-dama chad be-shabsa, arba, u-ma'ali shabsa*. So this is
like the time that it is appropriate to give blood, as opposed
to that was just like a spacing. The time to give blood
is Sunday, Wednesday, and Friday. Now, שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* you can't give
blood anyway because you know, it's a מלאכה *melacha*. But how about
the other days? How about Tuesday and how about Monday, Tuesday, and
Thursday? אבל שני וחמישי *Aval sheni va-chamishi*, so Monday and Thursday, לא
Lo, *lo*, you shouldn't give blood. דאמר מר *De-amar mar*, מי שיש
לו זכות אבות יצאת דם בשני וחמישי *mi she-yesh lo zechus avos
yeza'at dam be-sheni va-chamishi*. Somebody who has the merit of their fathers,
meaning who has extra stored-up merit, if you want to take a
risk, then you know, give blood on Monday and Thursday. So you're
really risking things. Why? שבית דין של מעלה ושל מטה שוין כאחד
*She-Beis Din Shel Ma'ala ve-Shel Mata shavin ke-echad*. Both the heavenly court
judges, because the heavenly court judges every day, and because the court
below judges Monday and Thursdays was the day of the judgment of
the court below. They would have regular you know, they would come
to the cities and judge on Mondays and Thursdays. So it's a
day of judgment. And because when you let blood, you are making
your body vulnerable, you know, you're weakening yourself, and as we discussed
yesterday, if you act in certain ways and you don't eat, you
get up right away, you could really you could really endanger yourself.
So don't take those risks on a Monday and a Thursday.
Now, how about Tuesday? That's the one day we don't have explained.
בתלתא בשבתא מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? לא? *Bislasa be-shabsa mai ta'ama lo?*
Why not on Tuesday? משום דקיימי ליה מאדים בזוגי *Mishum de-kaimei lei
Ma'adim bi-zuvei*. So because מאדים *Ma'adim* appears twice. So basically this was
the whole issue about the constellations and, you know, they believe there
was like these basically this like
there were seven constellations that would be on a cycle. I really
don't know I can't explain what it related to astronomically, but I
can tell you how the math works. Basically רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* you know, רש"י *Rashi* here spells it out. It's שצ"ם חנכ"ל
*ShTzaM ChaNKaL*, if you see that's like a beginning of an abbreviation
in רש"י *Rashi* about two lines above the תהלים Tehillim, *Tehillim*, which
is
שבתאי *Shabtai* Saturn, and then צדק *Tzedek*, which is צדק
*Tzedek* no well it's not a planet, I
think. What's צדק *Tzedek*? Is it it might be it might be
Jupiter. Is it? Yes, צדק *Tzedek* is Jupiter. Jupiter, okay, Jupiter, מאדים
*Ma'adim* is Mars, חמה *Chamah* is the sun, נ' *Nun* is נוגה
*Nogah* no, כוכב *Kochav* is Mercury, so what's נוגה *Nogah*? Venus. Venus.
Which one is Venus? נוגה *Nogah*. נוגה *Nogah*. Okay, Venus, and then
and then Mercury, and then ל' *Lamed* is לבנה *Levanah*. So anyway,
the moon. Somehow these seven are in a cycle, each one in
a different order, and to make the long story short, by Tuesday
it starts from how we understand it was when the world was
created and when these were put in the sky when the world
was created and they're on a seven they're like on a rotation
of seven hours. So, if you do the math, on Tuesday, מאדים
*Ma'adim* always appears in an מאדים *Ma'adim* always appears in an even
hour.
And in fact, in many languages, the day that we call Tuesday
is the etymology of the word is the day of Mars. Oh
really? That's very interesting. French and Spanish.
Huh. Okay, that's very interesting. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* particularly emphasizes
that it appears in an even hour. Actually Steinzaltz at the back
has a whole
chart. Anyway, Mars appears in an even hour on Tuesday and that
makes it particularly dangerous and Mars is blood. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara, says מה לי שבתא נמי טעימי בזיזי, ma lei shabsa nami
taimi b'zuvei, so even on ערב שבת Erev Shabbos as well, Mars
appears on an even hour, so apparently in the fourth hour. So
the גמרא Gemara. says כיון דדשו ביה רבים, keivan d'dashu bei rabbim,
because since it's very common to let blood on a Friday, maybe
it gets you hungry, you enter to שבת Shabbat. particularly with, you
know, good appetite especially because you had to eat after letting blood
and you had to eat on שבת Shabbos and they didn't have
a lot of money so might as well double it up. So
since that's a very common שומר פתאים ה', shomer pesayim Hashem, God
watches over the foolish. What can you do? It's already an established
practice so we can't go ahead and outlaw it. רב משה Rav
Moshe uses that logic in a particular תשובה teshuvah where he says
it's אסור assur to start smoking, but if you already smoking, you
know, what can you do? Nobody's going to listen to us anyway
so שומר פתאים ה'. shomer pesayim Hashem. Yes.
So they are almost kind of putting down the people that consult
the חוזים, chozim, you know, the
stars?
I don't know that they're always putting down the astronomers. They really
did believe, look, the belief in astrology was pretty widespread, you know,
even not only in the גמרא, Gemara in the ראשונים Rishonim as
well, like the אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra was very big into astrology
and all these things.
So but we're not supposed to do that.
Well, which exactly things, right, what exactly things fall into the, look,
it's a general question about all these issues about going to magicians
and necromancers and astrologers, whether the thing is all nonsense, which is
what רמב"ם Rambam says, or whether the idea is that, you know,
whether some people believe that all those things were true except you're
not allowed to pursue them. So then the question is, okay, but
maybe there's certain things which are allowed and certain things which aren't
allowed, you know. So this general sense of being aware that certain
times of days are, you know, are dangerous or whatever, you know,
for many of them that might have just been natural science, you
know, it's just taken for granted that on a, you know, on
a day when Mars is in the ascendancy you don't do certain,
you know, that's like, but that seems to be. I mean, again,
the רמב"ם Rambam writes about it, you know, about how, about how,
you know, he either says either they didn't mean it, or he
says that okay, they've got that wrong, you know, we've developed since
then our science has improved. But definitely even a lot of ראשונים
Rishonim really believed it, you know, till the so and certainly in
the גמרא. Gemara All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
שמואל, ארבע דהוא ארבע, arba d'hu arba, if you basically have, if
you have a Wednesday which is the fourth of the month, ארבע
דארבע עשר arba d'arba'is or Wednesday on the 14th, or ארבע דעשרין
וארבע arba d'esrim v'arba or Wednesday on the 24th, ארבע דליכא ארבע
בתריה arba d'leika arba basrei or Wednesday in which there is not
four days left to the month after it, so Wednesday towards the
end of the month, on all those things סכנתא, sakanta, it's a
danger to let blood on those days. Okay, ראש חודש ושני לו
חולשא, Rosh Chodesh v'sheni lo u'chusha, if you let blood on ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and the second day, by the way, אדר שמח
Adar Sameach to everybody,
so then you it particularly get weak. שלישי לו סכנה, shelishi lo
sakana, if you let blood on the third of a month, then
it endangers you. מעלי יומא טבא חולשא, ma lei yoma tava u'chusha,
if you let blood ערב יום טוב, Erev Yom Tov, it weakens
you. מעלי יומא דעצרתא סכנתא, ma lei yoma d'atzarta sakanta, if you
let blood on ערב שבועות, Erev Shavuos, then that actually endangers you.
וגזרו רבנן אכולהו מעלי יומא טבא משום יומא טבא דעצרתא. v'gazru rabanan
akula ma lei yoma tava mishum yoma tava d'atzeret.
And the rabbis said don't let blood on any ערב יום טוב
Erev Yom Tov because of ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov of
שבועות. Shavuos. I don't know what to say about all this. Okay,
so now why? דנפיק ביזיקא, d'nafik beizika, because on the day of
עצרת Atzeres a wind comes, ושמיה טבוח, u'shmei tavu'ach, and its name
is slaughtering, דאילו לא קבילו ישראל תורה, d'ilu kibel Yisrael Torah, because
had ישראל Yisrael not accepted the תורה, Torah, הוי טבח להו לבשריהו
ולדמיהו, havei tavach lehu levisraiyu u'l'damaiyu, it would have slaughtered their flesh
and blood. So therefore that day ערב שבועות Erev Shavuos is a
very dangerous day, you don't want to be doing certain types of
surgery or letting blood on that day. אמר שמואל, אכל חטי, acha
chita, if you ate wheat, רש"י seems to mean if you do
any eating right before you let blood, והיקז דם, v'hika dam, and
you let blood, לא היקז דם אלא סוחי חטי, lo hika dam
ela sochei chita, the bloodletting only helped for the food you just
ate. It did not really sort of was not more generally beneficial.
והני מילי לרפואה, v'hani mili l'refuah, that's if you're letting blood for
sort of like health purposes,
אבל לאקולי, aval l'akulei, if you're just doing it to like lighten
the blood, the blood is very weighty, I don't know what this
means, מעלי, meiyal, then it will work even if you've just eaten
right before. המקיז דם, hamakeiz dam,
if you let blood, שתייה לאלתר, shetiya l'alter, you can drink immediately
afterwards, אכילה עד חצי מיל, achila ad chatzi mil, and eating until
a half a מיל, mil, the time it takes to walk a
half a מיל, mil, which is like ten minutes. איבעיא להו, iba'yu
lehu, so they asked, שתייה לאלתר מעלי, shetiya l'alter mali, if you
drink right away it's good, אבל בתר הכי קשי, aval basar hachi
kashi, if you drink
after
it's bad for you, או דאמרינן לא קשי ולא מעלי, od d'amrinan
lo kashi v'lo mali, or do we say it's not bad and
not good after if you wait, if you don't if you drink
after it's good, if you wait it's neutral not good or bad,
תיקו, teiku, we don't know. איבעיא להו, iba'yu lehu, they asked, אכילה
עד חצי מיל הוא דמעלי, achila ad chatzi mil hu d'kamali, do
we say eating until a half mile that's when it's good, if
you eat right
after... הבתר הכי ומיקמי הכי Habatar hachi umikmi hachi but before and
after, קשי kashi it's bad for you? או דילמא o dilma לא
קשיא ולא מעלי lo kashya velo ma'ali or before and after it's
it's neutral? תיקו Teiku we don't know. Okay, מכריז רב Machriz Rav
now we're getting to the end of this. רב Rav announced:
מאה קרי בזוזא, Me'a kari bezuza, מאה רישי בזוזא. Me'a reishi bezuza.
So I'll read it the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. תוספות Tosafot
reads that basically this is a hundred heads for a זוז, zuz,
a hundred, I'm sorry, right, I'm sorry, hold on, I'm sorry. He
has the גירסא girsa of קרני. karnei. A hundred horns, they would
you know do bloodletting with a horn. A hundred horns for a
זוז, zuz, a hundred heads for a זוז. zuz. What תוספות Tosafot
says this means is that they would, that the cost for bloodletting
would be a זוז. zuz. So basically, so not you'd actually do
a hundred for a זוז, zuz, but like you know you'd be
announcing like you know however many people you want you know זוז
zuz per bloodletting. And for head, what does this mean? It means
for haircut, because the bloodletters and the barbers were the same people.
They had the sharp instruments. So yeah, that's the way תוספות Tosafot
reads it. Now מאה שפמי Me'a sepami for a hundred mustaches ולא
כלום velo klum you don't have anything, because if you're if you
pay for bloodletting or you pay for haircut, the mustache is thrown
in for free. Right,
that's what תוספות Tosafot says. ואמר רב יוסף Ve'amar Rav Yosef כי
הוינא בי רב הונא Ki havina be Rav Huna when I was
at the house of רב הונא, Rav Huna, יומא דמפגרי בי רבנן
Yoma demifagri be rabanan a day that the rabbis were sort of
like you know not sort of like lazy and
not sort of being too productive in their learning, אמרי amri they
would say האידנא יומא דשפמי הוא. Haidna yoma deshapmi hu. The day
is a day of the mustaches. ולא ידענא מאי קאמרי Velo yadana
mai kaamri I didn't know what they were saying, and now I
understand it. Because basically the idea of the mustache is that you
know is that you don't get the barbers didn't get paid for
the mustache, they threw it in for free. So therefore, if you
put in a lot of effort and don't get anything out of
it, or you don't put in a lot of effort anyway, you're
not getting anything out of your effort, so they would call that
it's a mustache day. So that's why the that's the day when
the learning wasn't going so well. Yeah.
Different societies back in this time had different customs regarding men's facial
hair. Do we know what things were like in בבל? Bavel?
No idea. I do know that there's discussions around חול המועד Chol
HaMoed about cutting your mustache if it's getting in the way of
your eating. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says וכורשין הטבור Vekorshin hatabur
let's wrap this paragraph, yeah.
This is again medical advice thrown in that has no relation to
הלכה halacha whatsoever.
I understand. It has relation if they, if we go through this
every time. Okay, if,
if there's a דעת תורה Da'at Torah approach and it's danger, so
I understand. But if they're seeing themselves as like you know leaders
of the community that people respect and pay attention to, they feel
therefore they have responsibility towards people's health and well-being. They want to
distribute helpful you know helpful medical advice.
Well they're saying if everybody does it, then שומר פתאים השם Shomer
peta'im Hashem God will take care of them.
Well, they're also no, I think they're also giving themselves a pass
why they feel that they can't do anything about it. We actually
think this is a bad practice but nobody's going to listen to
us so what can we do about it? So I think that's
also sort of what's being said there. But you know, like I
don't know if the rabbi got up and says I want to
remind everybody the importance of doing an annual checkup or whatever, you
wouldn't have a problem with that, right? But if the rabbi got
up and, you're what?
Annual checkups are useless.
Okay, fine, whatever. Yeah,
I don't know what to say Rivka, it's a problem in our
culture that there's a whole דעת תורה Da'at Torah
and the... Right. But I, but I do want to say is
that even in very you know חרדי Charedi ישיבות, yeshivot, they do
not treat deal with the גמרות Gemarot that deal with health advice
in the same way. They do not treat it as you know,
they might feel that their contemporary rabbis are all דעת תורה Da'at
Torah and תורה מסיני, Torah MiSinai, but I have yet to see
a ישיבה yeshiva where people read these גמרות Gemarot and take these
types of health גמרות Gemarot and take them you know with the
same type of weight that they take other גמרות. Gemarot. So I
think there's an understanding that these things are different. Yes.
The idea that certain times are dangerous though, I've seen that referred
to in a lot of writings and I mean I think
you mean the astrology.
Well not so much the astrology but I don't know what the
source is but they say that the early part of the night
is a particularly dangerous, right, right, right.
So that's true, that is true.
I think there was a thing that Tuesday is a lucky day,
is
a lucky day, right, and
they will only do rituals on...
right, that's true. That's definitely true.
Or on Christmas Eve.
Yeah, yeah, that is true. It's interesting the you know the things
that have to do with more sort of metaphysical beliefs, like you
know you know when is God דן בשמים dan bashamayim etc. was
given a lot more weight you know than the than these things
which are medical or the astrological or so on. You know the
things that were more about like how things work in the heavenly
spheres and the impact it has down here. That's true. All right,
so the you know let's finish up this paragraph. וכורשין הטבור Vekorshin
hatabur you can tie the umbilical cord on שבת. Shabbos תנו רבנן.
Tanu rabanan. וכורשין הטבור Vekorshin hatabur you can tie the umbilical cord.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אומר omer אף חותכין af chotchin
you can even cut the umbilical cord. וטומנין השליא Vetomnin hashilya כדי
שיחם
הולד kedei sheyeicham havlad now they once again they had this belief
that if you would bury the placenta. it would cause the fetus
to be warm so it would be health important for the health
of the fetus to bury the placenta. אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל:
Amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel: בנות מלכים טומנות בספלים. benos melachim tomos
b'sefalim.
Daughters of kings, meaning very wealthy people, would bury it in like
buckets, בספלים של שמן, b'sefalim shel shemen, in buckets of oil. בנות
עשירים בספוגים של צמר, benos ashirim b'sfugim shel tzemer, of
those that were rich would bury it in you know in a
wool like mats, not my whatever, you know wool
whatever sponges or you know whatever piles of wool. ובנות עניים במוכין,
u'vnos aniyim b'mochin, and
daughters of poor people would bury it in you know pieces of
cloth. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב: Amar Rav
Nachman Amar Rabba bar Avuha Amar Rav: הלכה כרבי יוסי. halacha k'Rabbi
Yossi. We rule like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that you could actually
cut the umbilical cord not just tie it. ואמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה אמר רב: v'amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabba bar Avuha
Amar Rav: מודים חכמים לרבי יוסי modim Chachamim l'Rabbi Yossi בטבור של
שני תינוקות, b'tabur shel shnei tinokos,
he would agree that if you have a umbilical cord of twins
שחותכין, shechotchin, you can separate the twins that are connected by the
umbilical cord. A twin fed by one umbilical cord, how's that work?
It depends on the type.
No, one umbilical cord, it's by one placenta.
Placenta, okay, but then they would be through the placenta connected to
one another. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama, Okay, מאי mai, טעמא, what's the
reason? דמנחי אהדדי, d'manchi ahadadei, because they pull one another and then
they can endanger one another if they're you know if they're connected
by the umbilical cord. So that even the חכמים Chachamim that generally
disagree here would agree. ואמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר
רב: v'amar Rav Nachman Amar Rabba bar Avuha Amar Rav: כל האמור
בפרשת תוכחה kol ha'amur b'parshas tochacha עושים לחיה בשבת. osim l'chaya b'Shabbos.
Anything said in the פרשה parsha of remonstration, which is a פרשה
parsha by יחזקאל, Yechezkel, where we see God is sort of like
point you know sort of remonstrating. Anyway, it speaks about what things
are done when they're born. These can be done on שבת Shabbos.
to a woman who has just given birth. Why?
שנאמר: she'ne'emar: ומולדותיך ביום הולדת אותך, u'moladosayich b'yom huledet osach, and your
birth on the day you were born, לא כרת שרך, lo kores
sarech, your flesh has not been cut, ובמים לא רוחצת, u'v'mayim lo
ruchatzat, you were not bathed with water, למשעי l'mish'i for health, where
were we,
והמללח לא המלחת, v'hamlei'ach lo humlachas, and you were not salted with
salt, רש"י says למשעי l'mish'i means to be smooth, anyway, and you
were not salted with
salt, והחתל לא חתלת, v'hachtel lo huchtalt, and you were not, which
the גמרא Gemara says means somehow like you were not like your
limbs were not arranged. So now it interprets it. ומולדותיך ביום הולדת,
u'moladosayich b'yom huledet, what?
It says swaddled here.
Swaddled, there you go. Good
translation. חיתול chitul is, oh right, in modern Hebrew חיתול chitul is
a diaper. Oh right, there you go. ומולדותיך ביום הולדת, u'moladosayich b'yom
huledet,
מכאן שמיילדין את הולד בשבת, mikan she'meyaldin es havlad b'Shabbos, you can
give birth on שבת Shabbos. to a you know you can assist
a woman, you can assist a woman in giving birth. All right,
it's הפעיל, hif'il, you can somebody else can assist a woman giving
birth. לא כרת שרך, lo kores sarech, מכאן שחותכין את הטבור בשבת,
mikan she'chotchin et hatabur b'Shabbos, to cut the umbilical cord on שבת.
Shabbos. ובמים לא רוחצת, u'v'mayim lo ruchatzat, water you were not bathed,
למשעי, l'mish'i, to smooth you, מכאן שרוחצין את הולד בשבת, mikan she'rochatzin
es havlad b'Shabbos, you can bathe the child on שבת. Shabbos והמללח
לא המלחת, v'hamlei'ach lo humlachas, מכאן שמולחין הולד בשבת. mikan she'molchin havlad
b'Shabbos. Apparently they would rub salt over a child, they believed it
was for health purposes. והחתל לא חתלת, v'hachtel lo huchtalt, מכאן שמלפפין
הולד בשבת, mikan she'melafpin havlad b'Shabbos, you can swaddle the child on
שבת. Shabbat הדר אמר מפנין. Hadar amar mafnin. Now the interesting thing
about this is we had that whole discussion what you can and
can't do, with no discussions of you know well the clear issue
was was that it was סכנת נפשות. But there was also no
discussions about what things were דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, what things were דרבנן. d'Rabbanan.
I mean, so just look at this small תוספות: Tosafos: כל האמור
בפרשת תוכחה. kol ha'amur b'parshas tochacha. תוספות Tosafos says לאו מקרא מפיק,
lav mikra mafik, it's not really learning it as a הלכה halacha
from the פסוק, pasuk, אלא מסתמא, ella mistama, כיון שבא בפרשת תוכחה,
keivan she'ba b'parshas tochacha, since it's pointing out these things were bad
things that had happened, אם כן צער הוא, im ken tzar hu,
so it causes pain
אם אין עושין, im ein osin, ובכולן אין בהם איסור דאורייתא. u'v'chulan
ein bahem issur d'Oraisa. None of these are biblical, like cutting the
umbilical cord, I mean what are you doing today? It's biblical. The
most probably biblical thing that could happen is if you do certain
cuttings that lead to bleeding you know, but that would not be
true in any of this type of stuff. So now we move
on because the last thing mentioned and not explored in the גמרא
Gemara was you do כל צרכי מילה בשבת, kol tzorchei mila b'Shabbos,
all things related to the
ברית מילה. bris mila. We now have the פרק perek called רבי
אליעזר דמילה, Rabbi Eliezer d'Mila which is devoted to the הלכות halachas
of מילה mila on שבת Shabbat, but also מילה mila in general.
This is where מילה mila gets its treatment. Any guesses why it's
called רבי אליעזר דמילה Rabbi Eliezer d'Mila and not just רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer? I mean it helps us understand what it's about.
I think because what the מוהל mohel of the day. I think,
I didn't check this, but is there a previous רבי אליעזר? Rabbi
Eliezer? Sometimes you have these things because they are because they are
clarified. There was an אמר רבי עקיבא. Amar Rabbi Akiva.
I might be wrong, I should have checked.
Anyway
yeah thank you, רבי אליעזר דהאורג. Rabbi Eliezer d'ha-oreg.
Right, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is אמר רבי אליעזר אומר האורג
שלשה חוטין בתחילה, Amar Rabbi Eliezer omer ha-oreg shelosha chutin bit'chila, but
of course there could have been the name of the פרק that
was given by you know obviously the גמרא Gemara didn't give these
names just האורג. ha-oreg. So you know but here you didn't have
a verb right after. What are you going to call it? אם
לא הביא כלי? im lo heivi k'li? So there you have רבי
אליעזר אומר האורג, Rabbi Eliezer omer ha-oreg, so anyway but we call
it רבי אליעזר דמילה Rabbi Eliezer d'Mila. so it shouldn't be confused,
it's רבי אליעזר דמילה. Rabbi Eliezer DeMila. Okay so and the next
one right is starts with רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Eliezer omer. so
we're able to call it תולין, Tolin, but there was no good
verb here, so and rather than just calling it רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, we call it רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, דמילה. So let's take
a look. רבי אליעזר אומר: אם לא הביא כלי מערב שבת מביאו
בשבת מגולה. Rabbi Eliezer omer: im lo hevi kli me'erev Shabbat mevi'o
beShabbat meguleh. If you didn't bring the, even the, the knife or
the various vessels on שבת Shabbat to the, this would be done
in the house of the child, you could even bring it on
שבת, Shabbat and, but you would do it exposed so nobody would
think that you are, carrying something you shouldn't be carrying. You make
it very clear you're carrying a מילה Mila knife on שבת Shabbat
which is allowed. You can violate שבת Shabbat for ברית מילה. Brit
Mila. Now that's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer we'll see רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva has some reservations. ובסכנה, Uvesakana,
now if there's a danger because meaning the non-Jews have prohibited ברית
מילה, Brit Mila, then מכסהו, mekhasehu, then מכסהו mekhasehu you hide it,
but על פי עדים al pi edim you have witnesses, witness that
you're hiding it so people should not suspect that you know if
you're carrying something under your garments they'll think maybe you're carrying something
else and you want it to be so at least people should
know, not the non-Jews but Jews should know that you're not carrying
that you're carrying only the מילה Mila knife. So you do it
so you hide it but, but people know what it, what's being
hidden. ועוד אמר רבי אליעזר, Ve-od amar Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer. would go so far as to say: כורתים עצים לעשות פחמים
לעשות ברזל. kortim etzim la'asot pechamim la'asot barzel. You could even cut,
cut down trees on שבת Shabbat to make charcoal and use the
charcoal to make, you know, the, the iron to help fasten the
iron to use for your מילה Mila knife. So basically anything if
you don't have another way to do it, anything you need to
do you can do for ברית מילה Brit Mila on שבת Shabbat
even many stages removed. That's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer So now comes
the pushback from רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. כלל אמר רבי עקיבא, Klal
amar Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, no, here's the
principle. כלל אמר רבי עקיבא: Klal amar Rabbi Akiva: כל מלאכה שאפשר
לעשותה מערב שבת אינה דוחה את השבת. kol melacha she'efshar la'asotah me'erev
Shabbat einah docha et haShabbat. If you could have done it before
שבת Shabbat. like making the knife you can't do it on שבת
Shabbat or bringing the knife where it has to be brought. ושאי
אפשר לעשותה מערב שבת, Veshe'i efshar la'asotah me'erev Shabbat, it could not
be done on ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, which is המילה hamila proper
because המילה hamila proper has to be on the eighth day and
could not be on a prior day, then דוחה את השבת docha
et haShabbat it overrides שבת. Shabbat Now he does not just mean
that like practically it couldn't be done, like let's say it's like
well you know the guy bringing the knife was on a plane
and he couldn't have gotten here before whatever it was blah blah
blah it doesn't matter. The point is in theory it could have
been done. Only things that in theory could not have been done
beforehand, which is basically just המילה hamila proper. Everything else in theory
could have been done earlier and therefore it doesn't override שבת Shabbat
and therefore you'll have to wait till מוצאי שבת Motza'ei Shabbat in
order to do it. Yes.
According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you would probably not have a
שבת Shabbat ברית Brit in a שול Shul because if you don't
have an עירוב Eiruv to carry the baby because
right.
Yeah okay. Exactly. Well they would anyway do it my,
my first son a שול Shul didn't hold by the עירוב. Eiruv.
So you did it in your house?
I didn't want to do it in my house. My wife didn't
want to do it in my house so we did, we found
a different שול. Shul.
Okay right but the the general practice was to do it in
the homes until pretty recently. Okay. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, so they
asked: טעמא דרבי אליעזר משום חבוב מצוה? ta'ama deRabbi Eliezer mishum chavuv
mitzvah? When רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you do it exposed, is
he saying when there's not a concern about you know about it
being prohibited from you know from from outside, so is it because
to endear the מצוה, mitzvah, so you want to publicize the fact
look how important this מצוה mitzvah is, I'm carrying on שבת Shabbos.
for its sake? או דילמא משום חשדא? O dilma mishum chashada?
Or maybe he's just saying that no you don't want people to
suspect you that you are you know carrying something you shouldn't be
carrying on שבת Shabbos. so you do it exposed. ולמאי נפקא מינה,
Ulemai nafka mina, what difference does it make? לאתויי מכוסה על פי
עדים, Le'atuyei makhuseh al pi edim, let's say you don't want to
carry it exposed, let's say you want to carry it you know
hidden and but you'll have people, witnesses, so that nobody will suspect
you. אי אמרת משום חבוב מצוה, Ei amrat mishum chavuv mitzvah,
if it's in order to endear the מצוה, mitzvah, מגולה אין מכוסה
לא, meguleh in makhuseh lo, you should דוקא davka do it exposed.
There's a real reason that you want to do it exposed even
if nobody will suspect you. אלא אי אמרת משום חשדא, Ela ei
amrat mishum chashada, if the whole concern is being suspected, אפילו מכוסה
שפיר דמי, afilu makhuseh shapir dami,
it wouldn't be a problem to do it hidden as long as
you address the suspicion concern. So מאי, mai? what's the הלכה? halacha?
מאי? אמר רבי לוי: לא אמר רבי אליעזר אלא לחבוב מצוה. Amar
Rabbi Levi: lo amar Rabbi Eliezer ela lechavuv mitzvah. He said it
to endear the מצוה mitzvah and therefore you make a point of
exposing it, which is consistent with his position that you can do
anything that's needed even multiple stages removed. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami
hachi, we've taught similarly: מביאו מגולה ואין מביאו מכוסה דברי רבי אליעזר.
mevi'o meguleh ve'ein mevi'o makhuseh divrei Rabbi Eliezer. So the fact that
it doubly underscores exposed not hidden says it's specifically supposed to be
exposed. אמר רב אשי מתניתין נמי דיקא, Amar Rav Ashi matnitin nami
dika, it's implied by the משנה, Mishna, דקתני בשעת הסכנה מכסהו על
פי עדים. dekatani bish'at hasakana mekhasehu al pi edim. In the time
of the danger you cover it. ובסכנה? Uvesakana? אין, In, when there's
a danger. שלא בסכנה? Shelo vesakana? לא, without a danger no, you're
not supposed to hide it. שמע מינה, Shema mina, משום חבוב מצוה,
mishum chavuv mitzvah, you see it's to endear the מצוה. mitzvah. שמע
מינה, Shema mina, that's a good proof. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we've
taught another ברייתא: Beraita: מביאו מגולה ואין מביאו מכוסה דברי רבי אליעזר.
mevi'o meguleh ve'ein mevi'o makhuseh divrei Rabbi Eliezer. Only exposed not hidden
when there's not, not a danger, what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer: says.
רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer,
now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reported in the name of רבי אליעזר:
Rabbi Eliezer נוהגים היו בשעת הסכנה שהיו מביאים מכוסה על פי עדים.
nohagim hayu bish'at hasakana shehayu mevi'im makhuseh al pi edim. So basically
it's when there was a danger then we would cover it and
hide it and there would be witnesses to see what we were
doing. So basically just another version of what we have in the
משנה. Mishna. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they ask the question. עדים דקאמר
איהו וחד, Edim d'ka'amar ihu vechad, when we say witnesses would see
that what it is, do we mean you and plus another person,
או דילמא איהו ותרי, o dilma ihu u'trei, or do we mean
two people other than you? תא שמע, Tashma, ובסכנה מכסה על פי
עדים, u'visakana mechaseh al pi edim, in the time of danger you
do it in front of witnesses, you do it in front of
witnesses. So אי אמרת בשלמא איהו ותרי שפיר, ei amart bishlama ihu
u'trei shapir, if it's you plus two others, that works, makes sense
with the text. אלא אי אמרת איהו וחד, Ela ei amart ihu
vechad, if it says you and another, מאי עדים? mai edim? What
does it mean witnesses? First of all, you can't be a witness
to your own thing, you know, you're a party of the issue.
Besides the grammar. So גמרא says שראויים להעיד במקום אחר. she're'uyim leha'id
b'makom acher. Alright, we don't necessarily mean that you're formally a witness
here, but the two of you, you and the other guy, could
be witnesses in another case, so maybe it just means plus one
more because you don't need real testimony here, you just need enough
that, you know, people will, you know, will, will not suspect you.
All right. So anyway, that's the idea about doing it in public
or hiding it. Now, why can't we put it off until מוצאי
שבת? Motzaei Shabbos? Because there's a מצוה mitzvah of מילה בזמנה. mila
bizmana. It's not because, whatever. So one of the things we learned,
so, yeah, so we haven't said it yet, but one of the
חז"ל Chazal learned, וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו, u'vayom hashmini yimol b'sar
arlato, וביום השמיני אפילו בשבת. u'vayom hashmini afilu b'shabbos. That somehow it
really means from the eighth day onwards. יצא Yotzei onwards you are
יצא yotzei ברית מילה, bris mila, but there's definitely this very strong
imperative to try to do it exactly on the eighth day. That's
how חז"ל Chazal understand the פסוק. pasuk. They understand that there's a
particular מצוה mitzvah to do it and it's such an important מצוה
mitzvah that it even, you know, that it, that it, that it
even overrides שבת. Shabbos. That's how, I mean, that's how they read
the פסוקים. pesukim. Right, that's how they read the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay,
we haven't said it, I mean it's assumed here, we haven't spelled
out the דרשה derasha here. Okay, but yeah. ועוד אמר רבי אליעזר,
V'od amar Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's, also said, now you
can even do multiple stages removed. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we
taught, במקום שרבי אליעזר, Bimkom she'Rabbi Eliezer, in רבי אליעזר's, Rabbi Eliezer's
you know, sort of town or city, where they followed his rulings,
היו קורצים עצים לעשות פחמים לעשות ברזל בשבת, hayu kortzim etzim la'asos
pechamim la'asos barzel b'shabbos, they would actually do this, they would chop
wood if they had to make, in order to get to, you
know, coals, many stages removed, in order to make the מילה mila
knife on שבת. Shabbos So the basic point being is that there
was not like, you know, consensus and universal opinion at the time
of חז"ל Chazal that everybody, you know, there was one ruling for
all of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, and there were localized places that
followed their authority. So in רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer, place, they followed
his authority. Something's never changed. במקום, Bimkom, now there is a question
within רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, how much לכתחילה l'chatchila can you go
ahead and do this, should you not try to do it beforehand?
A little bit this sounds like they wouldn't even care, they wouldn't
even go to the effort of taking care of it beforehand, they'd
just do it all on שבת. Shabbos, We'll see a little bit
more about that later, whether you were supposed to try to avoid
it, you know, minimize it according to him, but here it sounds
like not. במקום שרבי יוסי הגלילי, Bimkom she'Rabbi Yose HaGlili, in the
place of רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, היו אוכלין בשר עוף
בחלב, hayu ochlin basar of b'chalav, they would eat chicken with milk.
He ruled that there's no biblical and not even any rabbinic problem
of fowl with milk, and therefore they would go ahead and do
that. So, well, right that there's no biblical problem, but there is
a rabbinic, but he didn't hold of the rabbinic problem, and the
people followed him in his place. לוי איקלע לבי יוסף רישבא, Levi
ikla l'bei Yose Rishba, לוי Levi came to the house of יוסף
Yose the hunter. קריב ליה רישא דטוסא בחלבא, Kariv lei reisha d'tavsa
b'chelva, they brought him the head of some bird cooked in milk.
Well, I don't know what bird did it say? A peacock. Okay,
peacock and milk. לא אכל, Lo achal, he didn't eat it.
כי אתא לקמיה דרבי,
Ki
ata l'kamei
d'Rabbi, when he came to רבי, Rabbi, אמר ליה, amar lei, אמאי
לא תשמתיה? amai lo tshamtemehu? So רבי Rabbi said to
him, why didn't you put him in חרם? cherem? What is he
doing? You know, he's regularly violating a rabbinic prohibition of fowl and
milk. אמר ליה, Amar lei, אתריה דרבי יהודה
בן בתירה הוה,
asre d'Yehuda ben
Batera havah, no look, it
was the, it was the city of רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi
Yehuda ben Batera. He was the local authority. ואמינא, V'amina, I thought
to myself, דילמא
דרש כרבי יוסי
הגלילי,
dilma
darash k'Rabbi Yose
HaGlili, maybe רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Batera rules like
רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. דתניא, D'tanya, as it is taught
in a משנה, Mishnah, רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer,
נאמר לא תאכלו כל נבלה, ne'emar lo sochlu kol neveila, the verse
says do not eat any נבלה, neveila, any animal that, you know,
dies. ונאמר, V'ne'emar, and it says לא תבשל גדי בחלב
אמו,
lo
tevashel gedi b'chalev
imo, don't slaughter, don't cook a kid goat in its mother's milk.
So there's always the question of how you get from kid goat
in its mother's milk to general meat and milk. So רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili does it by the juxtaposition of נבלה. neveila.
נבלה Neveila is anything that has died, not just a kid goat,
any sort of, you know, animal that's died. אשר אסור משום נבלה,
Asher asur mishum neveila, something prohibited for נבלה, neveila, אסור לבשל בחלב,
asur l'vashel b'chalav, you can't cook in milk. עוף שאסור משום נבלה
יכול יהא אסור לבשל בחלב, Of she'asur mishum neveila yakhol yehei asur
l'vashel b'chalav, so maybe therefore it should include fowl because fowl also
is a, is a נבלה. neveila. תלמוד לומר בחלב אמו, Talmud lomar
b'chalev imo, its mother's milk. יצא עוף שאין לו חלב אם, Yatza
of she'ein lo chalev em, to exclude the עוף of that does
not have mother's milk. So therefore, now that's why it's not biblically
included. Everybody agrees that it's not biblically included, but somehow because he
emphasizes the פסוק pasuk of אמו, imo, of אמו, imo, that it
doesn't have mother's milk, for him that's understood to mean that he,
you know, that he even rabbinically thinks that it's just completely explicitly
excluded and is not even rabbinic. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak,
עיר... ir... time. So, meaning basically now, not necessarily that he's coming
to say we should rule like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, but I
think more to just say like nobody should cast aspersions, you know,
where they really, those places they really followed his authority and they
showed this tremendous, you know, love of this מצוה mitzvah of מילה,
milah, look what happened, everybody lived out to their ripe old age.
And not only that, but once the Roman government made an edict
on the Jewish people on מילה, milah, not to do ברית מילה,
bris milah, that one city somehow escaped the גזירה, gezeirah, escaped the
edict. So look, you know, so really it's very fascinating because you
would have thought חז"ל Chazal would have gone the opposite way. Oh
my god, this is such a dangerous idea and people are going
to be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos and we don't rule this way,
but even though we don't rule that way, they're making a point
about like, you know, about like the authority he had in his
location and the importance of it. Yes. Back to the תפסא, tafsa,
is this adequate proof that we could eat a peacock, that it's
kosher? If that's what the word תפסא tafsa means. All right. He
might have hunted it and then שחט shechted it. You do not
שחט shecht before the hunt. You can catch a peacock if you're
good. I don't know, I walk around the Bronx Zoo those peacocks
don't look too hard to catch. They're pretty elusive if you try
to because I tried to pet one. Oh really? Okay. Okay, תניא.
Tanya. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer. Now
we're going to follow this idea about like look how much they
treasured the מצוה mitzvah and look how they were rewarded. So we're
going to follow that theme particularly starting with ברית מילה bris milah
but broadening it. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
omer: כל מצוה שקבלו עליהם בשמחה, Kol mitzvah shekiblu aleihem besimcha, any
מצוה mitzvah that was accepted with joy, כגון מילה, kegon milah, like
מילה, milah, דכתיב שש אנכי על אמרתך כמוצא שלל רב, dechsiv sas
anochi al imratecha kemotze shalel rav, right a
פסוק pasuk we say during the ברית מילה, bris milah, I rejoice
on your
words like somebody who finds great treasure. Now how do we know
that's talking about ברית מילה? bris milah? So רש"י says it's your
word like singular, what was that one word, that one command we
had separate from all the other commands? That was ברית מילה bris
milah that was like the first command that Abraham received, that בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael received. תוספות Tosafos also says that that's the פרשה
parsha in תהלים, Tehillim, פרק in תהלים, that is למנצח על השמינית,
lamnatzeach al hasheminit, that starts with the eighth, the eighth day. Okay.
תוספות Tosafos also points out that the פסוק pasuk of אברהם Avraham
did a משתה גדול ביום הגמל את יצחק, mishteh gadol beyom higamel
et Yitzchak, the day that יצחק Yitzchak was weaned, he made a
big feast. So he quotes a דרשה drasha that הגמל Higamel is
ה' ג', hey gimel, which is equal to eight in גימטריה, gematria,
מל, mal, eighth day at the ברית מילה. bris milah. So anyway,
so you make a big סעודה seudah on the ברית מילה. bris
milah. Anyway, so anyone that was received with joy, ועדין עושין אותה
בשמחה, v'adayin osin osah besimcha, we do it with joy even till
today and we make a big feast and so on. וכל מצוה
שקבלו עליהם בקטטה, Vekol mitzvah shekiblu aleihem bekatata, any מצוה mitzvah that
originally was accepted with like you know dispute and anger and displeasure,
כגון עריות, kegon arayot, like when it came to the prohibition of
sexual relations, of forbidden sexual relations, דכתיב dechsiv it says: וישמע משה
את העם בכה למשפחתיו, Vayishma Moshe et ha'am boche lemishpechotav, משה Moshe
heard the people crying in their families, and the דרשה drasha is
על עסקי משפחתיו, al iskei mishpechotav, they were all crying because of
the prohibitions within the family of incest. So עדין adayin and they
were upset about those prohibitions. עדין עושין אותה בקטטה, Adayin osin osah
bekatata, then there's still are fights around those issues. דליכא כתובה דלא
רמו בה תיגרא, Delaka kesuvah d'lo ramu bah tigra, anytime there's a
כתובה kesuvah there's always going to be some dispute and debate about
the you know about the money in the כתובה kesuvah and so
on, so there's always like you know it remains complicated and contentious.
תניא, Tanya, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר: Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer:
כל מצוה שמסרו ישראל עצמן עליהם, Kol mitzvah shemasru Yisrael atzman aleihem,
any מצוה mitzvah that the Jewish people were willing to give their
lives over for, למיתה lemitah for death, בשעת גזירת המלכות bishat gezeirat
hamalchut when there was an edict from the government because that's when
יהרג ואל יעבור yehareg v'al ya'avor is extend to all the מצות
mitzvos when the government is trying to stamp out the religion, כגון
עבודת כוכבים, kegon avodat kochavim, like עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim ומילה umilah
and ברית מילה, bris milah, and they were willing to give up
their lives for that, this by the way reflects I think is
specifically referring to חנוכה, Chanukah, right and you know that we know
specifically about those, ועדין היא מוחזקת בידם, adayin hi mukhzaket beyadam, they
still are holding tight to this מצוה. mitzvah. They are very, you
know, וכל מצוה שלא מסרו ישראל עצמן עליהם למיתה, vekol mitzvah shelo
masru Yisrael atzman aleihem lemitah, anything that they did not give over
their lives for בשעת גזירת המלכות, bishat gezeirat hamalchut, כגון תפילין, kegon
tfillin, like תפילין, tfillin, ועדין היא מרופה בידם, adayin hi merufeh beyadam,
it's weak in their hands. Pretty funny like because if you would
say what's a thing that like is very you know is one
of the basic things done by observant Jews you would say for
males at least you would say it's תפילין, tfillin, but דאמר רבי
ינאי: d'amar Rabbi Yannai: תפילין צריכין גוף נקי כאלישע בעל כנפים. Tfillin
tzrichin guf naki k'Elisha Ba'al Knafayim. תפילין Tfillin require a clean body
like אלישע Elisha the master of wings. We'll see why he's called
that in a minute, but anyway but the point being that the
fact that it has to be emphasized means that not everybody is
doing it and it's hard thing presumably to do. So it shows
that תפילין tfillin is something that is not you know done as
well as it needs to be done. Now of course it's a
little funny to getting that out of that statement you could just
be saying that's what you have to do and then people do
it, people are careful about having a clean body but somehow there's
an understanding that maybe that's a very that is a high standard,
it's something hard to achieve but if so it's Nevertheless it is
worth noting that in the time of even the תוספות Tosfot they
talk about the problem that people were not doing תפילין tefillin as
well as they should have and they were not doing it on
a regular basis and so on. So it is something that whether
because of the demands of keeping a גוף נקי, guf naki, meaning
not passing gas, which is what this means, or whether just in
practice there was a feeling that תפילין tefillin was not done as
well as it needs to have been done. So now we're going
to talk... and those are excluded right? Because of those that exclude
women focus on the גוף נקי guf naki idea. Okay what that
has to do with women and does it have to do with
general attitudes about menstrual taboos and so on, that's a separate discussion.
Right, particularly in אשכנז Ashkenaz this whole issue about women and menstruation
went well beyond הלכות נידה. hilchos niddah. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said
אביי, Abaye, במאי, be'mai, where were we, what is the interpretation, I
jumped ahead, of this גוף נקי? guf naki? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
said אביי, Abaye, שלא יפיח בהם, shelo yafiach bahem, you can't even
pass gas with them. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, שלא
יישן בהם, shelo yishan bahem, you can't sleep with them even out
of a concern you'll pass gas. ואמאי קרו ליה אלישע בעל כנפיים?
Ve'amai karu lei Elisha Ba'al Knafayim? Why is he called this? שפעם
אחת גזרה מלכות הרשעה, Shepa'am achat gazra malchut ha'risha'ah, one time the
evil government Rome, גזירה על ישראל, gezeirah al Yisrael, this is a
famous story right, made an edict... this story has come up before?
Yes the story has come up before. Okay, yep, it came up
about three months ago or so. Okay, שכל המניח תפילין על ראשו
יקרו את מוחו, shekol hamaniach tefillin al rosho yiku et mocho, anybody
that puts תפילין tefillin on his head will have his head pierced
with like a spear, spear. והיה אלישע מניח תפילין, Vehayah Elisha maniach
tefillin, this person by the name of אלישע Elisha would wear תפילין,
tefillin, ויצא לשוק, veyatza lashuk, he would go out into the marketplace,
he would publicly demonstrate that he was wearing תפילין tefillin probably, you
know, to help in defiance, but to strengthen the resolve of the
Jewish people. וראהו קסדור אחד, Vera'ahu kasedor echad, a certain officer saw
him, רץ מלפניו, ratz milfanav, he ran away, רץ אחריו, ratz acharav,
and this guy ran after him, כיון שהגיע אצלו, keivan shehigia etzlo,
but when he was catching up to him, נטלן מראשו ואחזן בידו,
netalan merosho va'achazan beyado, he tore them off his head and held
them in his hand. אמר ליה מה בידך? Amar lei mah beyadecha?
What's in your hand? By the way, this shows that תפילין tefillin
were pretty small. The תפילין tefillin they found in the בר כוכבא
Bar Kochba caves were very small so you could hold the whole
thing in your hand. מה בידך, Mah beyadecha, what's in your hand?
אמר לו כנפי יונה, Amar lo kanfei yonah, oh, just feathers of
a dove. פשט את ידו, Pashat et yado, he opened his hand,
ונמצאו בה כנפי יונה, venimtza'u bah kanfei yonah, and you found feathers
of a dove. לפיכך קוראים אותו בעל כנפיים, Lefikach kor'im oto Ba'al
Knafayim, they called him the master of the wings, of the feathers.
מאי שנא, Mai shna, what, abracadabra, exactly, מאי שנא, mai shna, and
a dove flew out of his head. מאי שנא כנפי יונה? Mai
shna kanfei yonah? Why did he, of all the birds, did he
pick that one to say? דאמר ליה ולא אמר ליה שאר עופות,
de'amar lei velo amar lei shear ofot, and didn't say other birds?
משום דדמיא כנסת ישראל ליונה, mishum dedamya Knesses Yisrael leyona, because the
Jewish people are compared to a dove, שנאמר כנפי יונה נחפה בכסף,
shene'emar kanfei yonah nechpah bakesef, the feathers of a dove covered in
silver, ואברותיה בירקרק חרוץ, ve'evroteiha biyrakrak charutz, and its wings like fine
gold. Okay, מה יונה זו כנפיה מגינות עליה, mah yonah zu knafeiha
meginot aleiha, and the same way a bird its feathers protect it,
אף ישראל מצוות מגינות עליהם, af Yisrael mitzvot meginot aleihem, specifically a
dove, I don't get why specifically a dove, רש"י says a dove
uses more its wings to fight off attacks than its beak, I
don't know. Anyway, אף ישראל מצוות מגינות עליהם, af Yisrael mitzvot meginot
aleihem, similarly the Jewish people the מצוות mitzvot protect them. Anyway, so
here at least אלישע Elisha was taking it very seriously, but presumably
the reason he was doing it so much publicly was because nobody
else was, so it shows that they were not willing to be
מוסר נפש. moser nefesh. תוספות Tosfot brings down, there's a little disturbing
תוספות Tosfot here, אמר לו כנפי יונה, amar lo kanfei yonah, תוספות
Tosfot says הרי שלא מסר עצמו ולא אמר תפילין הם. harei shelo
masar atzmo velo amar tefillin hem. So תוספות Tosfot actually says that
even אלישע Elisha wasn't being מוסר נפש moser nefesh because he wanted
to save himself from being killed and he said that they were...
but that's pretty funny, I mean, my god, he was there doing
it in defiance and publicly, he just didn't want to get, yeah,
you don't have to go out of your way to get killed.
Anyway, but you know, that gets into issues again about the בעלי
התוספות Ba'alei HaTosfot and אשכנזים Ashkenazim and their willingness of martyrdom and
so on. Yes Charlie. I've heard that עבודה זרה avodah zarah and
מילה milah even non-religious Jews, particularly in the land of Israel, mostly
don't worship idols and mostly do ברית מילה, bris milah, it's fairly
widespread. Right, it's a good point, alright, it's a good point, very
good, yeah, true, it is extremely, right, universal, not even amongst non-observant.
Okay. אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, although the מילה milah thing
is now being, you know, well it's always getting challenged in different
ways. אמר רבי אבא בר רב אדא אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi
Abba bar Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak, פעם אחת שכחו ולא הביאו
איזמל מערב שבת. pa'am achat shachechu velo heviu izmel me'erev Shabbos. Now
we get to a little more הלכה. halacha. One time they forgot
and they did not bring the knife from ערב שבת, erev Shabbos,
והביאו בשבת דרך גגות ודרך חצירות, veheviu be'Shabbos derech gagot vederech chatzerot,
and they brought it on שבת Shabbos following רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer
they did it by ways of the rooftops and of the courtyards,
שלא ברצון רבי אליעזר, shelo birtzon Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
wasn't happy, he would have had them go straight in רשות הרבים.
reshut harabbim. And this gets again to the point, right, which is,
which is, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's so much allows it that he
even would say that if, you know, you could even straight away
violate even if it, you know, now presumably as long as the
other way was less, you know, as long If you have an
option of doing it with a way without violation, you can violate
if that is the more direct approach. That seems to be רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, position. תוספות Tosfos even points out why didn't they
for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer why do you have to bring the
knife, why didn't you just bring the infant to the knife and
then it's not carrying because if you say the principle of חי
נושא את עצמו. chai nosei et atzmo. So תוספות Tosfos says, well,
so he has explanations, maybe the mother can't come, she's not feeling
well, different explanations, but anyway in the end תוספות Tosfos says, maybe
just רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you do the more convenient thing,
even if it requires חילול שבת chilul Shabbos and it's more convenient
to bring the knife than to bring the infant. So when רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's allows it he really allows it with a large
degree of latitude and says, you know, it's more like sometimes there's
this discussion when we allow things on שבת, Shabbos פיקוח נפש pikuach
nefesh and others, do we say הותרה hutra or דחויה? d'chuya? Like
it's totally permissible or that it overrides, the prohibition is still there
but something overrides. If you say it's like the prohibition doesn't apply
at all, you have a lot more latitude, you don't have to
justify every particular nuance of what you're doing. And that seems to
be רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, position. So they brought, so because they
did it in this more roundabout way that it wouldn't be a
biblical violation, he was not happy. So the גמרא says מתקיף לה
רב יוסף, Maskif lah Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked, שלא
ברצון רבי אליעזר, she-lo b'ratzon Rabbi Eliezer, not, you know, against the
will of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer אדרבה, adaraba, the opposite makes sense.
רבי אליעזר הוא דשרי, Rabbi Eliezer hu de-shari, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
at least was happy that they did it altogether, you know, it
certainly wasn't with the will of the rabbis, the rabbis would have
prohibited even that. וכי תימא v'chi teima שלא ברצון רבי אליעזר דשרי
אפילו ברשות הרבים, she-lo b'ratzon Rabbi Eliezer de-shari afilu b'reshus harabim, so
maybe you want to read it says no, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would have allowed it even רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, so he was
unhappy that they did it in a roundabout way. So okay, so
who was it, so according to whom did they do it? אלא
ברצון חכמים? ela b'ratzon Chachamim? So rather what, they did it according
to the will of the חכמים Chachamim דאסרי דרך רשות הרבים ושרו
דרך גגות דרך חצרות וקרפיפות, de-asri derech reshus harabim u-sharu derech gagot
derech chatzerot u-karpifos, would that suggest that the rabbis say you only
can't do a biblical violation but you can do a rabbinic violation?
ומי שרי, u-mi shari, since when did they permit? They don't even
permit a rabbinic violation if it could have been done ערב שבת.
erev Shabbos. והתניא, ve-ha tanya, we've learned in a ברייתא, Baraisa, כשם
שאין מבינות אותה דרך רשות הרבים, k'shem she-ein mevinos osah derech reshus
harabim, the same way you can't bring it through רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, this is now the חכמים Chachamim speaking, כך אין מבינות לא
דרך גגות ולא דרך קרפיפות ולא דרך חצרות. kach ein mevinos lo
derech gagot v'lo derech karpifot v'lo derech chatzeros. You can't bring it
by rooftops and by yards and not by courtyards. So even though
those these things are only rabbinic, again all these things are a
רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, but the problem here is that first of
all if it's a חצר chatzer and it doesn't have an עירוב,
eiruv, you can't carry in the חצר. chatzer. But even if they
do, you can't carry from one to another. You can't carry from
one rooftop to another rooftop or from one חצר chatzer to another
חצר. chatzer. Those are considered to be separate רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid
unless you מערב m'arev all of them together. But even if they
all have sufficient walls, because they're separate רשות היחיד, reshus ha-yachid, you
can't carry from one to the other unless you do this עירוב
חצרות, eiruv chatzeirot, which is you join them all in some like
food and it's like they're all one place. So the rabbis would
not even allow a rabbinic violation. So here's saying, so who did
they do it according to? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wasn't happy because
he would have said go by רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, it's more
direct. חכמים Chachamim wouldn't be happy, they wouldn't want you to even
rabbinically violate. So who did they do it according to? אלא אמר
רב אשי, ela amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי, Rav Ashi, שלא ברצון
רבי אליעזר ומחלוקתו. she-lo b'ratzon Rabbi Eliezer machlokto. You're right, it was
not with the desire of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or those that
argue with him. Both רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wasn't happy with them
and the חכמים Chachamim weren't happy with them. So who was happy
with them? אלא ברצון רבי שמעון. ela b'ratzon Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon was happy with them. Because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually,
not about ברית מילה, bris milah, in general רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
feels you can carry from one חצר chatzer to another, from one
roof to another, you can do this, because they're all רשות היחיד.
reshus ha-yachid. דתנן, d'nan, in the following case: רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi
Shimon omer, אחד גגות אחד קרפיפות ואחד חצרות, echad gagot echad karpifot
v'echad chatzerot, whether rooftop or like a whatever field or a yard,
assuming again they all have sufficient walls around them, כולן רשות אחת
הן, kulan reshus achas hen, they're all considered one domain, not separate
domains, one single רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid לכלים ששבתו בתוכן l'keilim she-shavsu
b'sochan for vessels that began in them when שבת Shabbos began. If
you have a vessel you left in your yard or on your
rooftop then when שבת Shabbos began, then you can take it from
one rooftop to the next and from the rooftop to the courtyard
and from the courtyard to the field, all these things are considered
to be one genre and one רשות היחיד reshus ha-yachid even though
they're owned separately and even though they're, you know, in separate locations
and so on. They're all one domain if the thing began there
when שבת Shabbos began. So now why do you then have to
make an עירוב eiruv of it all, meaning the עירוב eiruv again
of the bread, not what we call the עירוב. eiruv. לא לכלים
ששבתו בתוך הבית. lo l'keilim she-shavsu b'soch ha-bayis. The only reason is
to take from the house into the courtyard. Okay, so you can't
take from a house if it began שבת Shabbos, in the house,
that's in a separate domain from the courtyard unless you make an
עירוב. eiruv. But something that began in the courtyard, all the courtyards
are considered one big unit. Okay, so you get it, the basic
point about this is all these things have walls, it's all רשות
היחיד. reshus ha-yachid. The only rabbinic problem is they're considered separate domains
and we demand normally an עירוב. eiruv. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
I don't demand an עירוב eiruv for things that began in those
domains, that's all considered to be one. It's only an עירוב eiruv
to move from the house to them or from them to the
house. But something that began there, that's okay. So this knife began
שבת Shabbos. in a courtyard and therefore according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, he was happy, it wasn't even a rabbinic violation. Okay. Had
a question? Yes. If the rabbis say that you can't do anything
except for the מילה milah itself on שבת, Shabbos so what do
you do in a situation where they actually did forget the knife?
What do you do? You wait to מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. So
they say you do it on Sunday? Right. You don't do it
then. Correct. בעי מיניה רב זירא מרב אסי. Baie minei Rav Zeira
meRav Assi. So רב זירא Rav Zeira asked רב אסי. Rav Assi.
מבוי שלא נשתתפו בו מהו לטלטל בכולו. Mavoi shelo nishtatfu bo mahu
letaltel bechulo. How about if you don't have a courtyard but you
have an alleyway that you do not have a שיתוף, shituf, can
you carry in it if vessels start in it? What this means
is, and this is going to be a thing that we're going
to see a lot when we get to עירובין, Eiruvin, is a
basic configuration was you have a lot of houses open up into
a courtyard, okay? So this is a בית, bayis, this is your
חצר, chatzer, and these are your houses. And then you have this
configuration, a lot of חצרות, chatzeros, a lot of courtyards, open up
into an alleyway, into a מבוי. mavoi. Okay? So you got that?
So it's houses into courtyard, courtyard into the alleyway. So if you
make an עירוב eiruv here, you can carry from the houses into
a courtyard. If you want to carry in the alleyway, all the
חצרות chatzeros have to get together and make an עירוב, eiruv, and
it's called a שיתוף מבוי shituf mavoi to allow you to carry
in the alleyway, which also has three walls but needs this. So
let's say you did not do this שיתוף shituf of the מבואות.
mavo'os. Okay. מהו לטלטל בכולו. Mahu letaltel bechulo. If a vessel began
in the מבוי, mavoi, can you carry in it? Is it like
the חצר chatzer that even without this עירוב, eiruv, you can at
least carry from something that began in it, you can carry within
it? מי אמרינן Mi amrinan do we say כחצר דמי, kechatzer dami,
it's like a חצר. chatzer. מה חצר אף על גב דלא עירבו,
Mah chatzer af al gav dela eirvu, the same way by a
חצר chatzer even if they didn't make an עירוב eiruv of the
houses, מותר לטלטל בכולו, mutar letaltel bechulo, something that started in it
could be carried in it, again because it has walls. האי נמי,
Hai nami, this too, אף על גב דלא נשתתפו בו מותר לטלטל
בכולו, af al gav dela nishtatfu bo mutar letaltel bechulo, even if
you didn't make a שיתוף, shituf, you can carry in it if
something started in it. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say
לא דמי לחצר, lo dami lachatzer, it's not similar to חצר. chatzer.
דחצר אית ליה ארבע מחיצות, Dechatzer is lei arba mechitzos, a חצר
chatzer has four walls, you know, three walls and then something on
the fourth side. האי לית ליה ארבע מחיצות, Hai leis lei arba
mechitzos, this even at the best-case scenario only has three walls. So
then we would only allow even when things begin in it only
if you make a שיתוף מבוי. shituf mavoi. אי נמי, I nami,
here's another difference. חצר אית ליה דיורין, Chatzer is lei diyurin, the
חצר chatzer is directly used by people who live in the houses
directly around it, so it's easier to conceptualize it as like a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid you can carry in. האי לית ביה דיורין,
Hai leis bei diyurin, an alleyway, right, does not have direct people
using it. You have to go from your courtyard into the alleyway.
So because people use it less, it's maybe less hard to conceptualize
it as a type of something as an extension of the house
or as a type of a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So anyway,
we might have higher criteria and if something, if you didn't do
this שיתוף, shituf, you cannot carry in it. שתיק ולא אמר ליה
ולא מידי. Shtik velo amar lei velo midi. He was silent, he
didn't have an answer, he didn't know. זימנין אשכחיה דיתיב וקאמר. Zimnin
ashkechei deyaisiv veka'amar. Then sometimes, however, he founds him that he was
sitting and saying. Now this was רב זירא Rav Zeira asked רב
אסי. Rav Assi. So sometimes רב אסי Rav Assi didn't know. But
then he found him in another time that רב אסי Rav Assi
was saying, אמר ריש לקיש משום רבי יהודה נשיאה, Amar Reish Lakish
mishum Rabbi Yehuda Nesia, that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said in the
name of רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, פעם אחת שכחו ולא
הביאו אזמל מערב שבת.
Pa'am achas shakechu velo heviu
izmel me'erev Shabbos. One time they forgot and did not bring the
knife from ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. והביאו בשבת. Veheviu beShabbos. And they
brought it on שבת. Shabbos They followed רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? maybe.
והיה הדבר קשה לחכמים. Ve'haya hadavar kasheh lachachamim. And the rabbis were
very disturbed. היך מניחין דברי חכמים ועושין כרבי אליעזר. Heich manichin divrei
chachamim ve'osin keRabbi Eliezer. How could they abandon the sages and go
like רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer So though we praised רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer. in the previous דף, here it's very clear what the הלכה
halacha is. חדא, Chada, first of all, here's why you shouldn't be
going like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer Number one, רבי אליעזר שמותי הוא.
Rabbi Eliezer Shamuti hu. He was שמותי, Shamuti, which either means he
was from the house of בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, so we don't
go like בית שמאי, Beis Shamai, but more simply what it means
is that he was put in חרם. cherem. The whole story about
the תנורו של עכנאי Tanuro shel Achnai and רבי Rebbi אליעזר and
whatever, he was put in חרם. cherem. So number one, you shouldn't
be going like him. ועוד יחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים. Ve'od yachid verabbim
halacha kerabbim. And anyway, he's just a minority opinion. ואמר רבי אושעיא,
Ve'amar Rabbi Oshaya, and so רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said, שאילתי את
רבי יהודה הגוזר, She'ilti es Rabbi Yehuda HaGozer, I asked רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda the cutter, the מוהל. mohel. So that was the phrase
they had for the מוהל. mohel. ואמר לי, Ve'amar li, and he
said to me, what happened with that story? How did they do
it? And he said, no, no, no, let me explain to you
what it was. מבוי שלא נשתתפו בו הוה. Mavoi shelo nishtatfu bo
hava. It was a מבוי mavoi that they didn't make a שיתוף,
shituf, they didn't all the courtyards get together, but still it was
all the knife started in the מבוי. mavoi. And when שבת began,
and it was a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So although ואייתוה מהאי
רישא להאי רישא, ve'aisyuha mehai reisha lehai reisha, they took it from
one end of the מבוי mavoi to the other end. So you
know, somebody seen it, they didn't realize, they saw somebody coming down
the alleyway with a knife. They thought that they had carried it
through רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, who knows what they thought, but it
was a knife that started in the alleyway and it was all
fine. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so then that's what רב אסי Rav
Assi said. So רב זירא Rav Zeira said to him, oh, so
obviously it sounds like you're allowed to carry something in a מבוי
mavoi that began שבת in the מבוי. mavoi. סבירא ליה למר מבוי
שלא נשתתפו מותר לטלטל בכולו? Sevira lei lemar mavoi shelo nishtatfu mutar
letaltel bechulo? So do you hold therefore that even if you didn't
make a שיתוף shituf in the מבוי mavoi if something began in
the מבוי mavoi you can carry in it? אמר ליה Amar Lei
ואמרי va'amrei אין in so רב אסי Rav Asi said yeah I
do hold that way. אמר ליה Amar Lei so רב זירא Rav
Zeira said זימנין בעיתי מינך Zimnin ba'ei minach many times I asked
you this question ולא אמרת לי velo amrat li and you never
told me that this was the הלכה halacha and here it's clear
from this story of ברית מילה bris milah that you feel that
that is the הלכה halacha if it starts in the מבוי mavoi
you can carry it in the מבוי. mavoi. אמר ליה Amar Lei
דילמא אגב שיטפך רהיט לך גמרך? Dilma agav shitpach rahit lach gamrach?
Maybe through your going through your learning your rushing through your learning
maybe you sort of discovered this? Meaning normally we say the opposite
that you know you're so quick in your learning you forget something
obvious. Here he's saying the opposite. He said you know normally when
I asked you didn't know the answer but now when you're doing
other learning and you're going through you came across this position this
discussion about רבי Rebbi and the ברית מילה bris milah and now
you realize this הלכה. halacha. אמר ליה Amar Lei אין in yes
you're right אגב שיטפא רהיטי לי גמרי agav shitpa rahiti li gamri
through my you know rushing through I discovered my learning basically I
came across this teaching of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and רבי about
the ברית מילה bris milah and I realized that actually that is
the הלכה halacha if something starts in the מבוי mavoi you can
bring it through the מבוי mavoi and that explains why they did
this. You're not even allowed to according to the חכמים Chachamim violate
rabbinic restrictions but you are allowed but this would be completely permissible
according to this approach if something starts there and it's all רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid even without a שיתוף shituf to bring it from
one end to the other and I guess we will well let's
try to read at least one more sentence. איתמר Itmar אמר רבי
זירא אמר רב Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav מבוי שלא נשתתפו בו
mavoi shelo nishtatfu vo אין מטלטלין בו אלא בארבע אמות. ein mitaltelin
bo ela b'arba amos. So this is a different this is an
opposing view. If you did not make a שיתוף shituf in a
מבוי mavoi even something that began in it you're limited to ארבע
אמות. arba amos. You cannot carry in it even if you know
if without a שיתוף. shituf. ואמר אביי Va'amar Abaye האי מילתא אמר
רבי זירא ולא פירשה hai milta amar Rabbi Zeira velo pirsha this
thing was said by רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira and was not explained
עד דאתא רבה בר אבוה ופירשה ad d'ata Rabbah bar Avuha upirsha
until רבה בר אבוה Rabbah bar Avuha came and explained it meaning
he did not mean it categorically it depends. דאמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה אמר רב Damar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha
amar Rav מבוי שלא נשתתפו בו mavoi shelo nishtatfu vo if you
have a מבוי mavoi that did not have a שיתוף shituf it
depends can you carry in it or not it depends. עירבו חצרות
עם בתים Eirvu chatzeiros im batim אין מטלטלין אלא בארבע אמות ein
mitaltelin ela b'arba amos לא עירבו חצרות עם בתים lo eirvu chatzeiros
im batim מותר לטלטל בכולו. mutar letaltel bekulo. This seems ironic and
we will leave it till tomorrow to explain what it means but
it means this case here if all the חצרות chatzeiros did what
they needed to do and made עירובים eiruvim then you can't carry
in the מבוי. mavoi. If however they did not do what they
needed to do and everything is open you can carry in the
מבוי mavoi and I will leave you to contemplate that paradox and
hopefully we will understand it tomorrow. Okay but anyway we actually got
caught up. Yay. We started.